Guide to the Time Inc. Fortune Publishing and Business Records 1929-2005 MS 3009-RG 25
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Fortune Publishing and Business Records
1929-2005
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 25
42.8 Linear feet in 45 record cartons including 6 reels of microfilm and 1 document case
The Fortune Publishing and Business Records contain materials from the offices and staff of the business and publishing side of the magazine's operation. The majority of materials are records from from the office of Publisher William Geer; advertiser record cards; and records from the offices of public affairs and promotions.
Arrangement
This record group is arranged in four series:
Series I. Publisher William Geer Files
Series II. Public Relations Department Files
Series III. Advertising Sales Department Records
Series IV. Fortune Data Bank Publications Fulfillment Files
Series V. Audiovisual
Historical Note
For the majority of Time Inc.'s existence, the company maintained a strict separation of editorial from the publishing and business side of each magazine, colloquially called the separation of "church" (editorial) and "state" (publishing). Publishing and Business Management includes the publisher, general manager, business manager, advertising sales, marketing services, letters, circulation, and public relations. The editorial side reported up to the editor-in-chief and the publishing/business side reported up to the corporate business executive which was the president prior to 1960 and the chief executive officer after. Henry Luce structured Time Inc. this way so that the business side could not (in theory) influence the editorial content of the publications. For example, the advertising sales people could not interfere with a magazine's decision to run an article on the dangers of cigarette smoking, even though it might mean losing millions of dollars in tobacco ads.
In September 1928, Time Inc. cofounder Henry Luce presented cofounder Briton Hadden with an idea for a new magazine. Luce wanted to create a magazine that would cater to the men who ran businesses in the United States. This magazine would offer business men a sophisticated perspective on industrial business and its role in society. To cater to this clientele, the magazine would feature richly illustrated pages as well as high quality editorial content. Hadden was not convinced that Luce's idea would work but agreed to let Parker Lloyd-Smith, a business writer at Time, and some researchers explore Luce's idea. In February 1929, not long after Hadden's sudden death, Luce went to the board of Time Inc. with his idea and proposed the launch of Fortune. At this meeting, Luce presented the board with a description of the magazine's appearance and an outline of its contents. This outline included samples of some articles that had already been written as well as illustrations. A few months after Fortune was proposed, the board agreed to proceed with the idea and the first issue of the magazine was released in February 1930.
Much like with Time, Luce named himself Fortune's editor. One of the first editorial decisions that Luce made was about how financial news would be presented. In other magazines and newspapers with similar content, facts and statistics were present in a straightforward fashion with no embellishment. To change this, Luce decided to hire literary talent instead of business experts or economists. Some of the talent that was recruited overs the years to work on Fortune included James Agee, John Kenneth Galbraith, Ernest Hemingway, Alfred Kazin, Dwight Macdonald, Archibald MacLeish, and Miné Okubo. Because Fortune was taking a more literary approach to its content, there were human interest stories alongside in-depth articles about major businesses and industries. In addition to the change in editorial material, Fortune also changed the approach to the advertisements and images used in the magazine. Instead of the standard black and white images, there was an emphasis on colorful advertisements and striking art, illustrations, and photographs. To make the imagery in the magazine stand out, Fortune recruited well-known artists and photographers. Included among those who have worked for Fortune over the years are Ansel Adams, Constantin Alajálov, John Atherton, Herbert Bayer, Lester Beal, Thomas Benrimo, Joseph Binder, Margaret Bourke-White, A.M. Cassandre, Thomas Maitland Cleland, Miguel Covarrubias, Walker Evans, George Gusti, Fernand Léger, Fred Ludekens, Erik Nitsche, Antonio Petruccelli, Diego Rivera, Ben Shahn, and Charles Sheeler. To receive a copy of this newly released magazine, members of the public needed to become subscribers. Despite there being no focus groups or trial issues to introduce buyers to the product, there were 30,000 subscribers at the time of the magazine's release. The initial copies cost $1 each or $10 for a yearly subscription. At the time, this was a steep price and was meant to act as a barrier so that only the most passionate and well off customers could afford to read it.
Fortune was well received by critics and industry professionals alike. By the end of 1930 and the release of the first eleven issues, the magazine's circulation had increased by 10,000 and was turning a profit for Time Inc. Despite the strong start, Fortune suffered difficulties after the end of World War II and was beginning to become unprofitable. At the same time that the magazine was experiencing financial trouble, members of Fortune's board of editors started to believe that the magazine was suffering from problems on the editorial side as well. Members of the board of editors suggested that the magazine had a lack of cohesion and no new ideas. Upon hearing these doubts, Luce decided to make some changes to the magazine and change its focus. The magazine would provide guidance to those interested in America's political economy. The changes upset the magazine's editors and writers, but renewed the interest of businessmen and helped increase the magazine's circulation.
Despite this somewhat tumultuous beginning, Fortune is still in print as of 2018. Over time the magazine has changed its publication schedule. Originally a monthly publications, the magazine became a bi-weekly publication in 1978 but switched to tri-weekly publication in 2009. While the magazine is primarily published in the United States, the magazine has had international editions as well. Many of these editions are no longer in print. These changes in Fortune's publication schedule coincided with an increase in demand for the magazine. With the growth of the magazine's popularity with the general public, editors and writers from Fortune began to make appearances on radio and television shows to share information found in the latest articles. The magazine also hosted its own short-lived television show Fortune Week which was on CNBC from 1993 to 1994.
Citations:
"About Us: Our History, Our Mission, Our Editorial Standards, and Who We Are." Fortune. July 20, 2018. Accessed November 08, 2018. http://fortune.com/about-us/.
"Background Information - Fortune Magazine in the 1930s." Fortune in the 1930s. Accessed November 08, 2018. http://xroads.virginia.edu/~1930s/print/fortune/background.html.
Brooks, Tim, and Earle Marsh. The Complete Directory to Prime Time Network and Cable TV Shows (1946-present). New York: Ballantine, 2000. Accessed January 07, 2019.
Elson, Robert T. Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise: 1923-1941. New York: Atheneum, 1968.
Elson, Robert T. The World of Time Inc: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise: 1941-1960. Edited by Duncan Norton-Taylor. New York: Atheneum, 1973.
Gibbs, Wolcott. "Time... Fortune... Life... Luce." The New Yorker. June 20, 2017. Accessed November 08, 2018. https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/1936/11/28/time-fortune-life-luce.4
Hooper, Bill. Email to Holly Deakyne, 10 June 2016.
Okrent, Daniel. "How the World Really Works." Fortune. September 19, 2005. Accessed November 08, 2018. http://archive.fortune.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2005/09/19/8272901/index.htm
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include contracts and consent forms. Restricted boxes include R42, 2868, 2911-2913, and 2919-2942. Unreformatted audiovisual and digital material in the collection is not accessible. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Information about the history of Fortune and additional records from the publishing and business offices can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39). Records from the editorial offices are in the Time Inc. Fortune Editorial Records (MS 3009-RG 8).
Scope and Contents
The Fortune Publishing and Business Records contain records from offices and staff from the publishing and business side of the magazine, not the editorial side. The staff represented include Publisher William Geer and Public Relations Director Emma Dockendorff. Additionally, there are departmental records from Advertising Sales and Public Relations along with collected audiovisual material relating to Fortune. This record group includes clippings, correspondence, notes, transcripts, drafts, press releases, press kits, photographs, video cassettes, audio cassettes, and open audio reels.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. 2015.
Audiotapes; Clippings (information artifacts); Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Press releases.; Press kits.; Public relations; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- History; Transcripts.; Videocassettes.; Dockendorff, Emma C.; Geer, William D., 1906-1976; Wood, Richardson, 1904-1976; Time, inc. -- Archives.; Time, inc. -- History.
- Series I. Publisher William Geer Files, 1929-1949; 3.35 Linear feet in 5 record cartons
  Biographical Note
  William Geer began working for Time Inc. as writer in 1929 after graduating from Yale. During his time as a writer, Geer assisted with the March of Time radio shows. In 1939, Geer was promoted to promotion manager for Time Inc. but changed positions the following year and became the assistant to the president. Geer remained in this position for two years before beginning to work for Fortune. It is unclear what Geer's first position with Fortune was. Some materials indicate that he worked as a general manager from 1942 to 1943 while others have him listed as a publisher for all seven years that he worked for Fortune. In 1949, Geer left Fortune and became associate publisher of Life. During his time as associate publisher, Geer also acted as a producer of the television series Crusade in Europe, which ran from 1950-1951 and was an attempted relaunched of the March of Time film series. In 1954, Geer retired from Time Inc.
  Citations:
  "William Geer Sr. of Time Inc. Dead." New York Times. August 23, 1976. Accessed January 3, 2019. https://www.nytimes.com/1976/08/23/archives/william-geer-sr-of-time-inc-dead-fortune-and-life-official-70-with.html
  Personnel and Organization: Department Head Lists. Time Inc. Reference Files (MS 3009-RG 3), The New-York Historical Society.
  Scope and Contents
  The Publisher William Geer files were created or collected by Geer during his time working for Fortune from 1942 to 1949 and contain materials from 1929 to 1949. Materials that date prior to 1942 are items that Geer used for reference. Additionally, Geer's files include materials from Richardson Wood, a member of Fortune's board of editors beginning in 1940. While Time Inc. in general kept a strict separation between the editorial and publishing sides of their enterprises, materials within this series indicate that Wood and Geer sent materials between each other and may have collaborated on some projects together.
  Materials in the series include lists of Fortune advertisers, lists of ad agencies, advertising order policy, drafts of ads and page layouts, answers to common questions about the ad department, chart of circulation expenses, clippings, plans for senior Fortune writers, department of labor reports, financial statements, outlines of department objectives, reports on circulation fulfillment, reports on circulation demographic problems, reports on the future of Time Inc., edit formula/plans, reports on operations, reports on comments concerning Fortune, and correspondence. The topics discussed in the correspondence include Fortune circulation, public perception of Fortune, new ad accounts, number of ads, estimated ad revenue, magazine ideas, meetings, complaints about Fortune ads, expenses, budgets, salaries, Newspaper Guild negotiations and election surveys.
  Arrangement
  Organized alphabetically.
  - Advertising, 1930, 1938-1946, undated (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 1-2)
  - Advertising Promotions: Magazine Comparisons, 1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 3)
  - Advertising Promotions: Miscellaneous, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 4)
  - Advertising Sales, 1942-1946 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 5)
  - Advertising Sales: Conventions and Meetings, 1947 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 6)
  - Advertising Sales: Miscellaneous, 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 7)
  - Alexander, Brooke, 1946 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 8)
  - Art Department, 1945-1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 9-10)
  - Black, Howard, 1945-1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 11-12)
  - Budget, 1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 13)
  - Budget Worksheets, 1945-1946 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 14)
  - Carlson, Arnold, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 15)
  - Circulation: Fulfillment, 1946 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 16-17)
  - Circulation: Fulfillment: Miscellaneous, 1946-1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 18)
  - Circulation: Miscellaneous, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 19)
  - Circulation: Newsstand: Young, Paul and Ralph Lindley, 1945-1946 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 20)
  - Circulation: Pratt, F.D., 1945-1946 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 21)
  - Complaints, 1944-1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 22-23)
  - Consumer Survey, 1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1946, undated (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: A-Z, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 26)
  - Dewey-Mieklejohn Debate, 1945 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 27)
  - Digest Permissions, 1945 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 28)
  - Dumbarton Oaks Pamphlet, 1945 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 29)
  - Edit: Galbraith, J.K., 1944 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 30)
  - Edit: Harris, W.B., 1945 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 31)
  - Edit: Miscellaneous, 1945-1947 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 32)
  - Edit: Survey: 1944 Election, 1944-1945 (Offsite-box 2901, Folder 33)
  - Edit: Survey: 1944 Election (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 1)
  - Edit: Survey: Fortune Readership, 1945 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 2)
  - Edit: Survey: Wood, Richardson, 1944-1945 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 3)
  - Edit: Wood, Richardson: Fortune Agreement, 1945 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 4)
  - Edit: Wood, Richardson: Fortune Agreement [RESTRICTED], 1945 (Offsite-box R42)
  - Empire State Move, 1944-1945 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 5)
  - Empire State Move [RESTRICTED], 1945 (Offsite-box R42)
  - F.A. Study, 1943 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 6)
  - Fortune Fans: Roper Survey, 1945 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 7)
  - Fortune Future, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 8)
  - Fortune: Memoranda: Miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 9)
  - Fortune: Memoranda: 1944 and Postwar: Budgetary and Business Program, 1943 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 10)
  - Fortune: Sales Meeting Proceedings, 1948 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 11-12)
  - Freedom of the Press Insert: 1947 April (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 13)
  - Future, 1947 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 14)
  - Gettell, Richard Glenn, 1945-1946 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 15)
  - Guild: Management Negotiations, 1946, undated (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 16-18)
  - Guild: Management Negotiations [RESTRICTED], 1945-1946, undated (Offsite-box R42)
  - Harrison, Richard Edes, 1943 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 19)
  - Holiday, 1948 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 20)
  - Infantry Journal Reprint: Japanese Issue: 1944 April, 1944-1945 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 21-22)
  - Interviews with Subscribers, 1939-1943 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 23)
  - Jessup Book: United States in a New World, 1944 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 24)
  - Jones, Alfred, 1945 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 25)
  - Larsen: Fortune Division Reports to, 1945-1948 (Offsite-box 2902, Folder 26)
  - Letters and Memoranda, 1948 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 1)
  - Library Survey, 1941 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 2)
  - Luce, Henry R., 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 3)
  - Magazine Digest, 1943 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Memoranda, 1942 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 5)
  - Murray, D.C., 1943 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 6)
  - New Fortune, 1948 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 7)
  - New Fortune: Blurbs and Comments, 1948-1949 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 8-9)
  - New Fortune: Directive Copies, undated (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 10)
  - New Fortune: Letters and Reports, 1929, 1944-1948 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 11-13)
  - New Fortune: Miscellaneous, 1948 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 14-15)
  - New Fortune: Progress Reports File, 1948 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 16)
  - New Fortune: William D. Geer Speeches: Advertising Sales Convention 1948 May and Executive Group 1948 Oct. 14 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 17)
  - Pepper, James W., 1946-1947 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 18)
  - Pepper, James W. [RESTRICTED], 1946 (Offsite-box R42)
  - Personnel: Miscellaneous, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 19)
  - Position: Wood Survey, 1945 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 20-21)
  - Production: Jersey City, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 22)
  - Production: Miscellaneous, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 23-24)
  - Renner, Dr. George T.: Teachers College, 1942 (Offsite-box 2903, Folder 25)
  - Roper, Elmo: Miscellaneous, 1948 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 1)
  - Trailer: March of Time: Wood, Richardson, 1943-1944 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 2)
- Series II. Public Relations Department Files, 1987-1991; 6.85 Linear feet in 7 record cartons
  Historical Note
  The earliest records of the Fortune Public Relations department are from 1987 and show Gary Belis as the department head. While the documents themselves do not list his exact role, the Time Inc. department heads list shows Belis as the head of the Publicity department. There is no indication, within the records or in any department heads list, of this department existing before 1987 though it may have been a part of another department, such as Promotions. Looking within the files themselves does not clear up this issue either since the work of Public Relations and Promotions appears to overlap. In 1991, the department was renamed the Public Relations Department. Between 1987 and 1991, there does not appear to be a consistent name for the department. In general, materials within the collection indicate that employees used the names Publicity, Public Affairs, and Public Relations interchangeably.
  The Public Relations Department Files contain materials created or collected by employees within the department between 1987 and 1991. Included in the series are clippings, transcripts, press releases, press kits, photographs, negatives, transparencies, pamphlets, reports, and correspondence.
  Arranged into five subseries:
  Subseries II.A. Public Relations Director Emma Dockendorff
  Subseries II.B. Public Relations Office Files
  Subseries II.C. Press Releases
  Subseries II.D. Television and Radio Transcript Files
  Subseries II.E. Newspaper, Radio, and Television Clippings Files
  - Subseries II.A. Public Relations Director Emma Dockendorff, 1989-1991; 1 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
    Emma Dockendorff was Fortune's Director of Public Relations between 1989 and 1993. Prior to her work at Time Inc., Dockendorff worked as an independent public relations and marketing consultant.
    "Emma Clurman, a Consultant, Marries." New York Times. May 18, 1985. Accessed January 03, 2019. https://www.nytimes.com/1985/05/18/style/emma-clurman-a-consultant-marries.html.
    Fortune Magazine Masthead. January 11, 1993. Vol. 127, No. 1. Accessed January 07, 2019. http://archive.fortune.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/1993/01/11/77385/index.htm
    The Public Relations Director Emma Dockendorff files cover the period of 1989 to 1991. The focus of the subseries is on managing the public's perception of Fortune, setting up seminars and events, and overseeing the work done within Fortune's Public Relations department. Included in this subseries are lists of public relations firms, clippings, lists of employees and responsibilities, lists of major ad market papers ranked by circulation, lists of sources for news about magazines, lists of major news syndicates, seminar schedules, to-do lists and notes, reports on broadcast market analysis, pamphlets from Quality Workforce Forum, press releases, Time Warner quarterly reports, lists and report on leading advertisers, reports on CEO crisis management and communication, photographs from 60th anniversary events, press kits, press releases and correspondence. The topics covered by the correspondence includes policies for sales and marketing staff, press release policies, ad sales, circulation statistics, and seminars.
    - Education Issue: Saving Our Schools, 1990 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 3-8)
    - Fortune Holds 20th Annual Worldwide Corporate Communications Seminar, 1991, undated (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 9-10)
    - Fortune Reports: Aug. 13, 1990 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 11)
    - Press Policy: Time Inc. Magazines, 1991 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 12)
    - Press Release Distribution Policy, 1989 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 13)
    - Public Relations Firms, 1991 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 14)
    - Public Relations Information, 1991 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 15)
    - Public Relations Seminar, 1991 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 16)
    - Quality Forum, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 17)
    - Quality Round Table Release: 1991 May 22 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 18)
    - Quarterly Reports: Time Warner, 1990 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 19)
    - Radio, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 20)
    - Research, 1989-1991 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 21)
    - Revenues, undated (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 22)
    - Sales Information, 1990 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 23)
    - Sales Staff, 1991 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 24)
    - Salt Lake City: 1990 Nov. (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 25-26)
    - Site Selection: Market Research, 1988-1991 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 27-28)
    - Sixtieth International Press, 1990 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 29)
    - Sixtieth International Tour, 1990 (Offsite-box 2904, Folder 30)
    - Sixtieth International Tour, 1990 (Offsite-box 2905, Folder 1)
    - Sports Illustrated for Kids, 1991 (Offsite-box 2905, Folder 2)
    - Strat Sherman, 1991 (Offsite-box 2905, Folder 3)
    - Time Insider, 1990 (Offsite-box 2905, Folder 4)
    - Time Magazine Fax List, 1991 (Offsite-box 2905, Folder 5)
    - Time Warner Inc. Earnings, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 2905, Folder 6)
    - Trump Coverage: Ad Age: 1990 July 25 (Offsite-box 2905, Folder 7)
    - Ulrich's International Periodicals Directory and Time Warner Corporate Information Packet, 1990 (Offsite-box 2905, Folder 8)
    - Video News Release, 1991 (Offsite-box 2905, Folder 9)